若いのう
（井口）安原(やすはら)っち
（絵麻）うっ
（絵麻(えま)）
なん… でもないです　すみません
（井口(いぐち)）
うん うん うん　どうした？
聞くは一瞬の恥
聞かぬは一生の恥ってね
What's wrong?
Animal Drawings
Nothing. Excuse me.
Yasuharacchi!
Better to ask and be a fool once than never to ask and be a fool forever.
Young 'uns these days...
Look at that, Rii-chan!
（かおり）
見て見て りーちゃん ちょうちん
写真 写真
Hey, take a picture!
Oh, right.
（みどり）あっ はい
（かおり）こっち来て こっち
Get over here!
You mean me?
えっ？　私ですか？
Look, a rickshaw! Hi!
（かおり）
あっ 人力車！　やっほ～！
やっぱ東京いいね～
Tokyo's really something, isn't it?
You think so?
（みどり）そうっすか？
（かおり）そうっすよ
Of course!
There are all sorts of people and places and stuff! It's awesome!
いろんな人 いろんな物
いろんな景色　すごいよ
And the country's not?
田舎は そじゃない？
Of course not!
全然！
We've been running our usual savings campaign, but there's been hardly any growth.
（支店長）
え～ ただ今 定期預金
キャンペーン中ですが
あまり伸びがありません
Be sure to get another 280 million yen's worth of new recruits.
あと２億8,000万円
勧誘をお願いします
Miyamori-san, can you come to the mixer this weekend?
（先輩ＯＬ Ａ）
宮森(みやもり)さん
週末の合コン 大丈夫そう？
I think so.
あっ 多分
高野(たかの)工務店の人たちでしたっけ？
They're from Takano Construction, right?
Yeah.
（先輩ＯＬ Ｂ）
そうそう　妻子持ちもいるのに
何が合コンだって話だけどね～
Some of them are married and even have kids. What a joke.
アハハ… 異業種交流ってことで
Let's just call it cross-industry networking.
（かおり）はあ…
（同僚）高野工務店っていえばさ
Speaking of Takano Construction,
did you see yesterday's Hamukatsu drama?
昨日のハムカツドラマ見た？
No.
ううん
女社長の話だっけ？
The corporation president in that is a woman, right?
The main character just pisses me off so much.
（同僚）
ハムカツ
ホント ムカつくんだよ
"I can cross this sea without a compass!"
“羅針盤がなくても
この海は渡ってみせる”って
All he does is talk about compasses.
羅針盤 羅針盤 言いすぎ
It's like characters in dramas
these days are broken records.
最近のドラマってさ
キメゼリフ言わせすぎだよね
ウッフフ…
Ah, Miyamori-san. About the break room...
（係長）
あっ 宮森さん
給湯室のことなんだけどさ
（かおり）
はい？
Yes?
There were tea leaves left in the strainer again.
（係長）
また三角コーナーに
お茶っ葉 残ってたよ
I told you to throw them all out, remember?
ちゃんとゴミ箱に
捨ててって言ってるよね
But I didn't make the tea yesterda—
あの 昨日のお茶当番 私じゃ…
Then tell whoever did.
（係長）
宮森さんから
当番の人に言っといて
Be sure to show that to the manager today.
（先輩ＯＬ）
それ今日中に部長に回して
Right.
あ… はい
Whoa! The Sky Tree!
（かおり）
スッカイツリー！
It's 634 meters tall!
（かおり）高さ634メートル！
（みどり）お～
（みどり）よく知ってるっすね
（かおり）常識でしょ 常識
Wow, you knew that?
I'm telling you, that's common knowledge!
I Don't Mean To Reproach You
Being able to support yourself is one thing,
but it's just as important to consider why you draw.
（杉江(すぎえ)）
食べていくのも大事だけど
なんのために描くかって
考えるのも大事だよね
I draw to support myself.
（絵麻）
生活のためです
（杉江）
安原さんは なんでアニメーターに
なろうと思ったの？
What drove you to become an animator?
I like drawing.
絵を描くのが好きだからです
Is that not enough?
それだけじゃいけませんか？
It's great to make a living doing something you like.
好きなことをして食べていけるのは
幸せなことだ
But after a while, it won't be enough anymore.
だけど そのうち描くだけじゃ
もの足りなくなってくる
You'll need a new goal.
何か新しい目標が
必要になってくるんだ
A new goal?
目標…
I want to make all the children around the world smile.
世界中の子供たちが
笑顔になってくれたら…
That's what I think about every time I draw.
僕は そう思いながら描いている
I can't even imagine having
that kind of ambition.
私は そんな大それたこと
全然 思えません
My big goal?
（太郎(たろう)）
最終目標？
そりゃ監督っしょ 監督
Becoming a director, of course!
Wait, you? A director?
（矢野(やの)）
はあ？　太郎が監督？
You know, like Miyazaki Isao or Hosokawa Yuzuru.
ミヤザキ･イサオとか
ホソカワ･ユズルみたいな
My name on a project and bam: instant success.
名前で客 呼べるようになって
With a huge following, even abroad.
外国にも熱狂的なファン作って
Then I could walk the path of glory down red carpets in Cannes, Berlin, Yubari, you name it!
カンヌとかベルリンとか夕張(ゆうばり)とか
レッドカーペットを歩くんですよ
ずいずいずいっと
（矢野）
まさか お前 演出志望だったの？
I had no idea you wanted to go down that route.
（太郎）
いや 俺は各話演出には
全然 興味ないんで
Well, screw directing episodes and all.
I just wanna be series director!
監督一本狙いっす
Need me to slap some sense into you?
殴ってやろうかな こいつ
（太郎）
え～ なんでですか？
What's your problem?
Every character designer and
animation director starts at tweening.
どんなキャラデ 総作監だって
最初は動画
Every director starts with individual episodes. Every producer starts as a PA.
どんな監督だって演出から
プロデューサーだって
制作進行から始めんだよ
I guess I could settle for producer.
じゃあ プロデューサーでも
いいっすよ
"Settle"?!
（矢野）でもだと？
（太郎）うわ…
え～ だってプロデューサーって
I mean, producers have to keep
sucking up to people all day long.
あちこちペコペコ
しなきゃいけないし
（落合(おちあい)）
ナベＰ
ペコペコしてたことあったっけ？
I don't recall NabeP sucking up to anyone though.
He's a special case.
（本田(ほんだ)）あの人は特別
（太郎）落合さん
Ochiai-san, you're going over to Canaan to become the head honcho, aren't you?
落合さんもカナンに行って
ブイブイ言わせるつもりなんでしょ
They got a ton of fine ladies there!
あそこ かわいい子 多いし
（落合）
やむにやまれぬ事情があんだよ
I have my own circumstances.
（太郎）
俺も やまれてえ！
I want to have my own circumstances too and work with Director Mijikai!
そんでもってミジカイ監督とかと
仕事してみてえっす！
変わってやろうか？
Want to switch with me?
For real?!
（太郎）マジっすか！
（落合）ウソだよ
No way.
Episode 1 might not even be done until the day of airing!
第一 １話から
当日納品になりそうなんだぞ
（太郎）
はい！　大変自慢 頂きました
Yeah, keep bragging about how hard it is, will you?
テスト前やってない自慢
寝てない自慢
I bet you don't study or get any sleep before exams,
そして業界忙しい自慢
and your work is the toughest too!
I'm not bragging. Just let me leave in peace.
自慢じゃねえって
もう おとなしく送り出してくれよ
Remember the musicians who kept playing even as people fled the sinking Titanic?
（太郎）
タイタニックから脱出する乗客に
演奏を続ける楽団員の気持ちは
分からんとですよ
（矢野）うちは泥舟かよ
（あおい）アハハ…
I don't recall boarding any ship.
本田さんも ゆくゆくは
渡辺(わたなべ)さんみたいに
Honda-san, will you eventually become a line producer like Watanabe-san?
ラインＰになるんですか？
I'm not really sure.
どうだろうね～
演出と監督が違う仕事みたいに
Just as EDs and series directors have different roles, producers and PMs' jobs are different too.
デスクとＰも違うからね～
（あおい）
じゃあ 一番なりたいものって…･
Then what do you want to become?
Well...
うんとね… ケーキ屋さん
A confectioner.
That sounds like a kindergarten girl's dream!
（矢野）
なんですか その幼稚園の
女の子みたいな夢！
This is my first time hearing this. Are you serious?
初耳
…っていうかマジバナですか？
Gross!
（太郎）キモッ！
（本田）夢なんだよ
It's my dream, okay? Come on!
夢なんだから
ほっといてくれよ！
Leave me alone!
ほお～ 全然 知りませんでした
I had no idea.
結構 これでも休みの日は
自分で作ってみたりしてんだよ
I try making stuff on my days off, you know.
あ～！　こないだの
あのブラウニー もしかして！
You mean like those brownies the other day?!
Yup, homemade!
うん 手作り
I don't know what to say...
うわ～ 複雑
They weren't bad, were they?
（本田）
え～ ちゃんと できてたよね？
いや おいしかったです
おいしかったんですが
Oh, it's not that.
They were actually delicious.
It's just... I thought I already had a clear mental image of you,
なんだろう
自分の中に予断と偏見があって
本田さんが新妻エプロンをつけて
卵を泡立てたのかと思うと…
so I just can't picture you wearing a cute apron, beating egg whites...
（本田）
新妻エプロンなんてしないから！
（太郎）
キモッ…
キモッ キモッ！
I don't wear cute aprons!
Gross! Gross squared!
（興津(おきつ)）
皆さん 少し
静かにしてください
Would you please quiet down?
Sorry!
（あおい）
あっ すみません
Oh right, it's time for the filming meeting.
（本田）
そうだ そうだ
撮影打ちの時間だ
You forgot about it?
（太郎）
あっ 忘れてたんですか？
It's your episode!
（本田）
お前の話数だろ！
Everyone has their dreams...
みんな 普通に
夢とかあるんだな～
Yeah, they're all working hard to achieve them.
（ロロ）
そうそう　みんな夢に向かって
頑張るんだよ
That's what life's all about.
それが生きるってことだよ
（ミムジー）
え～？　夢とか目標とかって
別にいらなくない？
Huh? Who cares about goals and dreams?
Why are you always raining on my parade, Mimuji?
ミムジーは どうして そんな
殺伐としたことばっか言うんだよ
It's all a trap.
なんか うさんくさいじゃん
People with their heads in the clouds are blind to reality.
“夢 夢”言うヤツに限って
現実 見えてないし
You got me.
あ痛～
You're so bitter, Mimuji.
（あおい）
ミムジーは相変わらず辛辣(しんらつ)だな
I'm a realist.
リアリストなんだよ
（エンジン音）
うわわ！
Dammit! Not again, Miyamori Aoi!
（富ヶ谷）
クッソ～！
また宮森あおいかよ！
肉離れじゃなかったんですか？
I thought you pulled a muscle.
うん 肉離れ
I did.
So how can you ride your bike?
なんで 自転車こげるんですか？
Well, next week is a hill-climb tournament.
それがさ 来週
ヒルクライムの大会があってね
What is that?
ヒルクライム？
It's basically a race where you ride your bicycle uphill indefinitely.
（木佐）
簡単に言うと自転車で坂道を
延々と上る競技なんだけどね
Unlike in normal road races, differences in weight, strength, and skill become really obvious.
普通のロードレースと違って
体重と体力と実力が
ハッキリものをいうんだよ
敵はいるけど本当の敵は
むしろ自分？　みたいな
There are other riders out there,
but the guy I really want to beat is myself!
It's all about pushing yourself past your limits!
追い込んで 追い込んで… こうね
I'd rather you finish and get past that work you're supposed to do.
私としては木佐さんが仕事を
追い込んでくれないと困ります
Of course! I want to enter the tournament without being weighed down by anything.
追い込む 追い込む
晴れ晴れとした気持ちで
大会に出たいもん
（あおい）う～ん
（木佐）だから ちょっと気分転換
This is just a little break to clear my head.
Thirty minutes! That's it, I promise!
ほんの30分！　ホントだって
仕事大事
でもヒルクライム入賞も夢なんだ
Work is important, but winning the hill climb is my dream!
うん？　夢？
Your dream?
そう！　夢！
Yeah, my dream!
See you in thirty! I mean it!
（木佐）
ホント30分だけ！　だけ！
Oh, cut it out already, Sis!
もう ねいちゃん なんなん？
もう！
Jeez!
（チャイム）
（あおい）おはようございます
Good morning!
Miyarmori Aoi here from Musashino Animation!
武蔵野(むさしの)アニメーションの
宮森です
（あおい）
今日は これで全部です
This is all for today.
やっぱり あしたが ちょっと
大変になりそうで すみません
Tomorrow could end up a being bit rough after all.
I'm sorry.
It's okay. I can handle this.
（瀬川(せがわ)）
大丈夫　まだ余裕
宮森さんこそ
13話いきなり任されて
But you must be having a hard time too,
what with having episode 13 dumped on you like that.
気ぃ緩めてらんないでしょ
…ってことは落合さんのこと
ご存じなんですか？
So you've heard about Ochiai-san's situation?
I got a call from Canaan.
カナンから電話があったから
They said they got my number from him.
落合君から
電話番号 聞いたって言って
They wanted me to help with RoboPub.
「ロボはる」
手伝ってくれないかって
I turned them down, of course!
速攻で断ったよ
I said I had Exodus and couldn't pick up another show.
「えくそだすっ！」が終わるまで
掛け持ちはできませんって
Thank you so much!
ありがとうございます
Pretty audacious of Ochiai-kun, huh?
落合君 彼なかなか太いよね
I'm sorry.
（あおい）
すみません
ううん
彼も上に行きたいんだろうな
He must want to move on up too.
He'll be PM for RoboPub after all.
「ロボはる」はデスクらしいし
Huh? He said nothing of the sort earlier!
（あおい）
えっ！
さっき何も言ってなかったのに
When was that?
さっき？
We were talking about our dreams in the studio this morning.
（あおい）
制作同士で
なんになりたいかって話を…
He seems rather ambitious to me.
あ～ 彼 結構 野心家だと思うな
You can tell?
分かるんですか？　そんなこと
I've been in the industry for a while.
（瀬川）
だって もう業界 長いし
いろんなタイプ知ってるからね
I've seen all kinds of people.
You're amazing, Segawa-san.
すごいです 瀬川さん
（瀬川）あっ そうだ それでね
（あおい）うん？
Oh yeah. That's right.
How did it go with Yasuhara-san? Did she say something?
安原さん どう？
なんか言ってた？
U-Uh... Not really.
あっ… いえ その 別に
She was like, "I guess I gotta try harder!"
…っていうか“頑張らないと”
みたいなことを言ってました
I see.
（瀬川）
そっか
うまく伝わってるといいんだけど
I just hope she didn't misunderstand.
I'm sure she'll be able to do it properly soon.
きっと もう少ししたら
安原さんも普通に
できるようになることなんだよ
You need to keep all the people who work with your drawings in mind.
自分の後の工程のことを考えて
描くなんてことは
But she doesn't know that yet.
Because of that, she can't quite do it.
でも今は まだ分からない
分からないから できない
It's a subtle thing, but important.
ちょっとの違いなんだけどね
So Ema's...
じゃあ 絵麻…
Yasuhara's keyframes aren't bad, right?
安原の原画がダメってことは
ないんですよね
Well, they're not bad.
えっとね　ダメじゃない
でも いいとも言えない
But they're not good either.
I see.
そうですか
I hope she manages to get over the hump.
うまく乗り切ってくれるといいな
Oh, you want to use the sink? Go ahead.
あ～ 流し どうぞ
Iguchi-kun,
井口君
ちょっと頼みがあるんだけど
I have a bit of a request for you.
ハァ ハァ…
Don't waste any paper.
（井口）
紙をムダにしない
Lineart (Aya & Kitten)
You picked this cut for yourself?
（井口）
このカット
自分で選んだんだっけ？
Yes.
あっ はい
Why?
（井口）
なんで？
Oh, I'm just curious, that's all.
いや 責めてるんじゃないからね
Because I've never drawn
keyframes of cats or any animals.
理由はネコとか動物の原画って
描いたことがなかったので
ほうほう
ここ日常芝居で大変だけど
It's hard because it's an everyday life scene,
but you get to show Aya with a childish expression.
あやが子供っぽい表情見せる
いいシーンなんだよね
Yamada-san's love for Japanese movies really shines through.
山田(やまだ)さんの日本映画愛
さく裂って感じ
It's a big part of the dramatic impact.
ドラマ的にも なにげに肝だよ
The cat's not anthropomorphized either.
It's just a regular cat.
ネコもさ 擬人化された
ネコじゃなくて本物のネコでさ
You don't get a chance to draw something like this every day.
あんまりないよね～
こういうの描くチャンス
（絵麻）力不足でした
（井口）うん？
I'm not good enough for it.
Hm?
I couldn't make the cat look cute at all.
全然 自分が描いたネコが
かわいいと思えなくて
I ended up drawing something that only resembled a cat.
ネコ的な何か別の生き物みたいで
フフッ 的な！
Cat-like!
面白いよ 安原っち
あんた やっぱ面白い子だね
That's pretty funny, Yasuharacchi!
You're really fun!
So what happened? You forgot what you were supposed to do?
それって なんつうの？
ゲシュタルト崩壊？
Lineart (kitten)
Lineart (Aya)
Like, "Is that what it looks like?"
これって こんなんだったっけ
…みたいな気分に
なっちゃって でしょ？
Yes.
（絵麻）はい
（井口）あるある 分かる～
I know exactly how you feel! Totally!
えっ 井口さんでもですか？
It even happens to you?
“でも”って何？
井口さんも 総作監の綸子(りんこ)はんも
Is it that surprising?
Chief AD Rinko-han and I are no different when the block hits.
煮詰まる時は同じだって
Um...
（絵麻）あの…
（井口）うん？
So what am I supposed to do?
そういう時は
どうすればいいんですか？
Is the only way to keep on drawing?
やっぱり描くしか
ないんでしょうか？
Even if I think it looks lousy and unacceptable,
自分の絵が
すごく下手なものに見えて
Animal Drawings
全然 納得いかなくても
リテークの予感があっても
and I'll have to retake it...
But with the deadline... you have to keep on drawing no matter what, right?
締め切りがあるし
やっぱり描くしかないですよね
あのね そういう時はね… 散歩
You know,
when you feel like that,
go for a walk!
Video    Photo    Square    Panorama
Yay! Tea time!
イェ～ お茶タイム
（シャッター音）
おっ 待っててくれたの？
Were you waiting for me?
Go ahead and dig in, Rii-chan!
どうぞ 食べて 食べて
りーちゃん
Um...
（みどり）あの…
（かおり）うん？
Is this really okay?
いいんすか？　遊覧バスとか
展望台のチケットとか
You paid for the tour bus, the observation deck ticket,
and now this super-expensive cake too.
超高級ケーキとか
全部 出してもらって
フフッ いいの いいの
カネならある
Of course it's okay!
I've got money!
I came here ready to spend away!
お金 使おうと思って
こっち来たんだもん
Rii-chan, is there anything you'd like?
りーちゃん 何か欲しい物ない？
I'll buy it for you!
ねいちゃんが買ったげる
I don't really need anything.
（みどり）
いや 今は別に
Then something you wanna do?
（かおり）
じゃあ やりたいこと！
There must be something!
やりたいことないの？
あるでしょ？
Like having dinner on a boat or going to a drag show!
ディナークルーズ
行くとか
ニューハーフの
ショーパブ行くとか
Something I wanna do?
（みどり）
やりたいこと…
Yeah! A dream! A wish!
うんうん 夢！　野望！
I want to write a story.
物語が… 書きたいです
I just got hooked on Dost... oevsky
and I was thinking about how interesting it is...
あっ いや 今 ドストエフスキーに
はまってて
すごいな～ 面白いな～って思って
The Brothers Karamazov?
「カラマーゾフの兄弟」？
Yeah! That Dost!
そうそう！　そのドストっす
I see, Dostoevsky!
You're smart, after all.
そっか～ ドストエフスキー
りーちゃん 頭いいもんね
いや 全然っす　ドスト読んで
物語とか なんかもう～
Not at all! I just happened to fall in love with the story.
Anyway, let's just do what you want to do!
それよか かおちゃんねいさんが
やりたいことやりましょう
Huh? Me?
（かおり）え～ 私？
（みどり）うんうん
Yeah! We did a lot of things today that I'd never be able to experience on my own.
今日とか自分一人じゃ
絶対経験できないことばっかなんで
It was a great experience!
むちゃくちゃ ためになります
An asset for both heart and mind!
頭と心の財産っす
An asset?
（かおり）財産か～
（みどり）ですです！
Yup-yup!
Aoi
Incoming Call
Hello?
（かおり）
もしも～し
Would you stop sending me pictures of all the fun you're having today?
（あおい）
ねいちゃん ねいちゃんの
物見遊山報告もういいよ
（かおり）
え～ ちょっとくらい
自慢させてよ
Come on, let me brag a little.
（あおい）
信金の人に送ればいいのに
Forward the pics to your co-workers or something.
（かおり）
イヤだ
No.
Why?
なんで？
Because it's an asset for me and Rii-chan!
（かおり）
私とりーちゃんの
絶対財産だもん！
Asset? What now?
財産？　何？
ねいちゃん フリーダムすぎ
She's really taking advantage of her freedom.
Freedom? You mean the director?
フリーダムって監督？
No. Never mind, it's nothing.
あっ 違います 違います
By the way, I saw Iguchi-san leave with Yasuhara-san earlier.
そういや さっき
井口さんと安原さんが
出かけてったけど
なんか知ってる？
You know what's up?
Huh? She left?
えっ？　出かけ？
えっ？　井口さん？
With Iguchi-san?
Sounds like you don't.
知らないね
Looking for Yasuhara-san?
（杉江）
安原さん？
R-Right.
あっ はい
I believe she went out for a walk.
散歩だと思うよ
（あおい）
散歩？
A walk?
Um, I don't really have the time...
あの 私 時間なくて…
How many frames have you gotten through since this morning?
（井口）
朝から何時間 座って
何枚 進んだ？
The block's acting like blinkers on a horse mask.
（井口）
煮詰まるってのはさ
こうなってるんだよね
You need some wide-open scenery to reset your sense of perspective.
だから広い景色が必要なわけ
Scenery?
（絵麻）景色？
（井口）うん
Yeah!
It's fifteen minutes by bike.
Straight down the road.
（井口）
自転車で15分 ほぼ道一本
知らなかったでしょ
Never been here, have you?
はい… 全然
I haven't...
If you're going for a walk to clear your mind, staying near the studio won't cut it.
息抜きとか散歩とかって言っても
会社の近くじゃ あんまし
そんな気分にならないっしょ？
I can definitely recommend this spot.
It's my little secret.
ここ おすすめ　私の隠し球
Is it really okay to share it with me like this?
（絵麻）
そんな場所 教えてもらって…
（井口）
いいの いいの
ドーナツもらったし
Yeah, of course!
Besides, I got to eat your donut.
Rinko-han showed it to me.
私も綸子はんから
教えてもらったんだから
Ogasawara-san?
（絵麻）
小笠原(おがさわら)さんですか？
She said Sugie-san showed her.
（井口）
綸子はんは杉江さんから
教えてもらったんだって
You know, Sugie-san is quite—
杉江さんね あの人 結構…
あっ お前 ニャ次郎(じろう)！
Look at that! It's Meowtwo!
Hello there, Meowtwo! You been doing well?
う～ん ニャ次郎
元気だったか～？
The first animal I drew was a mole.
私が初めて描いた動物
モグラだったよ
A mole?
モグラ
Do you think moles move slow or fast?
モグラって動き速いと思う？
遅いと思う？
（絵麻）う～ん… わ…
（井口）分かんねえっつうの
No idea, right?
It was a character-centric story, so it ended up okay, but still.
まあ キャラものだったから
なんとかなったけどね
Because you were already good at that point?
（絵麻）
それは やっぱり井口さんが
うまかったから…
Only good at copying, if you ask me.
うまかったとすれば
マネがうまかったんだよ
マネ…
Copying?
There's no way anyone can start off drawing that well.
最初からオリジナルで
うまく描けるわけないじゃん
Musani used to be quite big,
despite how it is now. Did you know that?
ほら ムサニだって
今はくすぶってるけど
昔 すごかったの知ってる？
I guess.
（絵麻）
あっ はあ… まあ…
So I went to the storeroom and looked for the keyframes of shows I loved.
（井口）
だから 倉庫 行って
昔 好きだった作品の原画とか
見してもらって
I imitated the ones I liked.
自分が描きたいって思う原画
マネして
Rinko-han always rejected the work I did,
綸子はんにダメ出しくらって
マネから自分なりの
表現できるように四苦八苦して
so I practiced until I could draw my own way instead of plain copying.
So is it okay to copy like that?
（絵麻）
マネしていいんですか？
そうだよ
どんどん見ていいんだよ
Sure it is!
Go on and try it!
How else would you improve?
それ以外に
どうやってうまくなる
Newbies examine their seniors' work and copy the movement patterns.
新人は先輩が描いた
動きのパターンをつかんでマネする
Think about your own style once you've got that down.
自分なりの表現ってのは
それから
パターン
Patterns?
Learning and copying are the same.
学ぶっていうのは
マネぶって言うじゃん？
Everyone starts out copying someone else.
みんな 最初は誰かのマネ
Every last person.
おんなし おんなし
So this is a cat's heel!
（絵麻）
ネコのかかとって ここなんだ
Yup, they walk on their toes.
あ～ そうそう
つま先立ちなんだよね こいつら
Do they not have kneecaps?
ひざの皿ってないんですか？
えっ？　そういえば…
どこだろうね
Now that you mention it, where are they?
ニャ～
（井口）
あ～ ごめん ごめん
Sorry, sorry!
（井口）ああ
（絵麻）なんか こう…
Ah, like this...
Can you draw it?
描けそう？
Director, were you as shocked as we were?
（円(まどか)）監督
（木下(きのした)）うん？
（円）
やっぱ ショックなもんですか？
When we didn't make it to airtime? Well...
（木下）
オンエア落とした時？
そりゃ もうね～
（円）
それじゃなくて 落合ですよ 落合
No, I meant Ochiai.
Ah, Ochiai?
あ～ 落合
Oh, so that's your reaction to it?
（山田）
なんだ その程度ですか
Not at all!
（木下）
いや！　いやいや…
ショックはショックだけど
Of course I was shocked.
You know what they say: "Welcome whoever comes and don't chase after those who leave."
あっ でも まあ 来る者拒まず
去る者追わずの精神で
Though I guess maybe I should've ran after her.
いや まあ 今 考えたら追うのも
ありだったかなとも思うけど
（山田）
元嫁の話はしてないですから
We're not talking about your ex-wife.
酔っ払いメールも
やめたほうがいいですよ
Lay off texting her when you're drunk too.
You say you shouldn't chase after those who leave,
（円）
去る者追わずって言うけど
過去にこだわり 振り回され
but seeing how you're a prisoner of your past,
I'd say you can't let go of anything.
監督は結構
ため込みタイプじゃないですか
I don't need you to tell me!
That's how I got this fat!
悪かったな！
だから太っちゃうんだよ
知ってるよ！
Anyway, I'm more worried about my future than Ochiai's!
落合の将来より
俺の明日をなんとかしてほしいよ
I'm making no progress on the second half of the storyboards.
あ～ 絵コンテ後半 進まねえ
I'd rather you didn't waste all your energy dwelling on the past.
（山田）
この期に及んで総力戦の
焼き畑農業は勘弁してくださいよ
Nothing gained and no one's happy.
（円）
後に何も残らない
誰も幸せにならないっていうね
I know!
（木下）
分かってるよ～！
Good evening!
お疲れさまで～す
Yamada-san, please check these keyframes.
山田さん
原画チェックお願いします
（山田）
うお～い あと何カット？
Okay.
How many more cuts?
32.
32カットです
Could you wait a little longer for Yasuhara-san's cat scene?
あの～ 安原さんがやってる
ネコのシーンなんですが
もうちょっと待ってもらっても
いいですか？
Why?
（山田）
えっ？　なんで？
She seems to be having a bit of trouble with it.
本人 ちょっと悩んでるみたいで
（円）
え～ さっき 井口さんと
I saw her chatting happily with
Iguchi-san on her way back though.
結構 楽しげに話しながら
帰ってきてたけど？
（あおい）えっ？
（木下）へえ～ 井口さんと
With Iguchi-san?
I never would have guessed.
珍しい取り合わせだな
I thought Yasuhara-san was the quiet,
introverted type, so I was pretty surprised.
安原さんって引っ込み思案かと
思ってたんで
ちょっとビックリしたんだよな～
Sis? Where are you now?
（あおい）
あっ ねいちゃん 今どこ？
No, I'm not mad!
もう 怒ってないよ
It's a bit late, but wanna have dinner together?
ちょっと遅いけど ごはん一緒に
食べられないかと思って
Huh?
え！　え！　なんで？　も～う
But why?
Wait for me! I'll be there in half an hour!
ちょっ ちょっと待って
30分で行く
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Araki-san
Ema
Asai-san
Asuka
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Araki-san
Ema
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Group Overview                             All
Onodera-san
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Asai-san
Asuka
Araki-san
Igarashi-san
Ishida-san
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Group Overview                             All
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Ema
Group Overview                             All
Itou-san
Imai-san
Uesugi
Ueda-san
Ueno-san
Ema
Okamoto
Okada-san
Odagiri
Onodera-san
Ema
Group Overview                             All
Matsu
Tei
Food and drinks
Kubota - Fried Fish
Denshu - Fried Chicken
Pretty boy - Sashimi
（戸が開く音）
（あおい）こんばんは
Good evening!
Hey, Oi-chan-senpai!
あっ おいちゃん先輩
And... she's asleep.
…って寝てるし
She couldn't handle all the freedom.
余裕のフリーダムっぷりっす
Sorry for always making you tag along with her.
（あおい）
ごめんね りーちゃん　昨日から
ずっと つきあわせちゃって
No problem. I had a blast!
いや 新鮮だったっす
Hey there! Where's Ema?
（しずか）
お疲れ～　絵麻は？
She was so focused I didn't want to bother her.
すごい集中してたから
声はかけなかったんだ
Work comes first, I guess.
仕事の邪魔しても なんですもんね
Zuka-chan, you're good for tonight. Why not drink something?
ずかちゃん 店はもういいから
ちょっと飲んでいきなよ
Will do! Thank you!
（しずか）
飲みます　ありがとうございます
Cheers! To us!
（あおい･みどり）
ま～す！
（しずか･あおい）お疲れ～
（みどり）お疲れさまです～
Is Ema gonna be all right?
（しずか）
絵麻 体 大丈夫なのかな
She used to get tonsillitis pretty often, remember?
あの子 時々 へんとう腺とか
腫らしてたりしたじゃん？
I think she'll be fine now.
う～ん 多分 もう大丈夫かも
（しずか）えっ？
（みどり）どっちなんすか？
What do you mean? Why "now"?
それに“もう”って
Did something happen?
なんかあったの？
Kinda. When I last checked,
it looked like that was all in the past.
ちょっとだけ　でも さっき
すごいいい感じで仕事してたから
I see. Glad to hear.
そっか　そんならよかった
（みどり）
あの おいちゃん先輩
Um, Oi-chan-senpai...
Hm?
We should totally make an anime.
That's right, all of us in the Animation Club!
ホントのホントに
アニメーション同好会のメンバーで
アニメ作りましょうね
I think we're the perfect team for it!
We've got the potential!
（みどり）
我々 最強メンバーだと思うんす
ポテンシャルは
Potential?
ポテンシャル？
I'll do my best and write an awesome story!
私も ものすっごい物語を
書けるように頑張りますから！
Let's do it!
おう 頑張ろう！
Okay...
I have the drive, anyhow,
though I don't know about the budget.
やる気だけはあるんで
お金とかそういうのは
分かんないですけど
あっ
かおちゃんねいさんがいるっす
But we have your sister!
Great idea!
（しずか）
いいね
偉くなってもらって予算もりもり
She should work her way up and finance it!
We'll take a top-down approach to anime!
トップダウンでアニメ化決定
んなの 無理に決まってるっしょ
Not a chance, of course.
You're awake?
起きてた
You can never know!
（しずか）
分かんないですよ
私 声優 諦めませんから
I won't give up on becoming a VA. You shouldn't give up either!
かおちゃんねいさんも ぜひ
ぜひって
On what?
Just five years! I'll debut in five years!
（みどり）
あと５年っす
５年以内にデビューしときます
Three! Make that three!
３年 ３年にしよ
Roger.
了解っす
But I'm almost 30 already...
え～ 私もうアラサーだよ
Isn't that great?
（しずか）
ちょうどいいじゃないですか
Is it?
（かおり）え！　いいの？
（みどり）区切り
Yeah, 30 is a turning point!
（しずか）
おいちゃんは
プロデューサーだからね
Oi-chan, you'll be the producer!
Producer?
プロデューサーって
Let's take a photo!
Kou-chan-neesan, if you would! Thanks!
写メ 写メ　かおちゃんねいさん
お願いしまっす
Now? A photo?
（かおり）今？　撮るの？
（みどり）撮ります 撮ります
Yeah! A record of us, our determination, and this moment!
覚悟と記念と人間の記録っす
あっ ねいちゃん その格好
Sis, why are you all dressed up?
I'm going back.
うん 帰る
Should I come with you to the station?
（あおい）
駅まで送ってくよ
It's okay. You've got work to worry about.
いいの いいの
仕事あるんでしょ
I put some dried radish strips in the fridge.
切り干し大根の炊いたの
冷蔵庫に入れといたから
And the potatoes started sprouting, so eat them quick.
じゃがいも 芽 出てるから
早めに使うこと
じゃあね お邪魔さま
Well then, I'm off.
Um, Sis?
（あおい）あっ ねいちゃんさ
（かおり）うん？
Are you okay? Everything fine now?
もういいの？　大丈夫？
フフッ まんず頑張っぺ
I'll do my best for now.
Hello? I'm not an employee of Musa—
I'm Director Kinoshita.
Next time on Shirobako:
What Do You Think Was the Message?
"What Do You Think Was the Message?"
（木下）
もしもし？　あ～
私 あの ムサニの社員じゃ…
あ～ 私 監督やってる木下です
次回
「ＳＨＩＲＯＢＡＫＯ(シロバコ)」